<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The state of the Navy consider'd in relation to the victualling, particularly in the Straits, and the West Indies with some thoughts on the mismanagements of the Admiralty for several years past : and a proposal to prevent the like for the future / humbly offer'd to the honourable House of Commons by an English sailor.</title>
            <author>English sailor.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93827</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5323</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42893</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875910</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875910</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152409</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93827)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152409)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2296:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The state of the Navy consider'd in relation to the victualling, particularly in the Straits, and the West Indies with some thoughts on the mismanagements of the Admiralty for several years past : and a proposal to prevent the like for the future / humbly offer'd to the honourable House of Commons by an English sailor.</title>
                  <author>English sailor.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for A. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 16, "A Catalogue of Books written against a Standing Army, and sold by A. Balwin [sic]."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Royal Navy --  Supplies and stores.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152409:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE State of the Navy CONSIDER'D In relation to the VICTUALLING, Particularly in the STRAITS, and the WEST INDIES.</p>
            <p>WITH Some Thoughts on the Miſmanagements of the ADMIRALTY for ſeveral Years paſt; and a Propoſal to prevent the like for the future.</p>
            <p>Humbly offer'd to the Honourable Houſe of Commons, by an Engliſh SAILOR.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second Edition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>A. Baldwin</hi> in <hi>Warwicklane,</hi> 1699. Price 3 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152409:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152409:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:152409:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152409:3"/>
            <head>The State of the Navy conſider'd In relation to the VICTUALLING, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Miſmanagements of the Navy ſince this Revolution have been ſo abominable, that they could never have been born at ſuch vaſt expence, but by an eaſy People, fond of a Government of their own ſetting up, and of a King ſutable to the Genius of the Engliſh Nation, and worthy of Immortal Honor, notwithſtanding the Male-Adminiſtration of the Officers employed under him. Will not fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Ages bluſh at the inſenſible Temper of their Forefathers, when they ſhall read of the eſcape of the <hi>Thoulon</hi> Fleet into <hi>Breſt,</hi> and the abominable Affair of Monſieur <hi>Pointi?</hi> When they read the horrid Stories of our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gull'd out of Mony rais'd for publick Service, and diverted to private and ſiniſter Ends, will they not wiſh thoſe Sums had been tranſmitted to them to be employ'd in more generous Atchievements? But as Clouds of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ariſe over the more clear Underſtandings and wiſeſt Heads, ſo Nations ſometimes become delirious, and hurry into Ruin, till kind Heaven remove the pernicious Frenzy. Had the Miſmanagements of the Navy tended only to the Conſumption of our Wealth, the Loſs might have been repaired; but when our Sailors are poiſon'd by bad Proviſions, or ſtarv'd for want of good, the loſs is irreparable. Thus the Blood of War is profuſely ſpilt in louzy Hammocks, ſtagnated with noiſom Scents, and the flower of our youthful Sailors ſmothered in unſucceſsful and needleſs Voyages, who might have won to themſelves and the Nation immortal Wreaths of Honour in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Attempts upon the Enemy. This Decreaſe of Seamen looks more like a Deſign upon the Engliſh Nation, than the effect of Providence. He that abandons himſelf to a moroſe Temper in his ſickneſs, and will not take ſuch Specificks as are eſſential to his Recovery, is a <hi>ſelo de ſe:</hi> And ſuch Officers as deny neceſſary and good Proviſions for Sea Service, can deſign no other than the Deſtruction of the Sailors, and conſequently of the Nation. They undermine our National Walls, I mean our Shipping, which without Men are but Floating C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtles, meer Machins of War altogether indefenſible. The Hardſhips of the Sailors have indeed been worthy the Conſideration of our Repreſentatives in Parliament. But poor Creatures, they have no body to repreſent their Grievances, they are tumbl'd and toſs'd on the watry Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152409:4"/>perhaps 18 or 20 Months together in the <hi>Straits,</hi> and as ſoon as they arrive in the Channel are turn'd over to other Ships bound to the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> or other Parts, and not ſuffer'd to come aſhoar and tell their Tale; or if they land, the neceſſitous good-natur'd Creatures ſell their Tic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets for half the worth, bouze it about in a Can of Flip, or a Bowl of Punch, forget their Sorrow, and remember their Miſery no more. If any Complaints have been made, it has been done by the ſtarv'd Wives and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Children of Mariners; if they have complain'd to thoſe Officers that ſhould have done them Juſtice, they might as well have told their Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Winds and devouring Billows, the treacherous Sands, and fatal Rocks, the natural Enemies of their Relations. Have they complained to Parliament? What Redreſs could they expect from ſuch a Parliament as the laſt and preceding Parliaments, ſo full of Courtiers, Judges of their own Cauſe, and Auditors of their own Accounts? The laſt Seſſions of Parliament the poor Labourers, Artificers, and others, belonging to the Victualling-Office, petitioned for Arrears of Wages due to them; the Committee that exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined the Caſe, conſiſted moſt part of the time but of ſeven Perſons, when (I am told) according to the Cuſtom of Parliament they ought to have been eight: four of the ſeven I knew to be Commiſſioners and Officers, and two of the four Perſons complain'd againſt; tho the Caſe was clear that they had ſome fifteen, others twelve, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Months due to them, and at the ſame time the Commiſſioners and Officers received their Salaries quarterly, yet a Report of the poor Mens Caſe was never made to the Houſe. But the Caſe of the Sailors is far worſe than others; they have no Time, no Acquaintance, nor Intereſt to proſecute any thing of this Nature, and thoſe that abuſe and cheat 'em have got the Weathergage of them, they can ſend 'em at any time on a long Errand to the E. or W. <hi>Indies</hi> far enough out of hearing: upon their return the Complaint is grown as mouldy as their Bread, and as ruſty as their Pork and Beef have been during the Voyage, and therefore ought to be caſt without Survey.</p>
            <p>The Sailors Caſe is indeed deplorable, kept long without pay, ſometimes fix years, forc'd to ſell Tickets to raiſe a little Mony for their Families at half value, tho as good and brave Engliſhmen as any; are altogether enſlav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and without any Law that I ever heard of impreſt, their Liberty taken from them, which when gone they are effectual Slaves; impriſon'd on board Ship, caned and kick'd by Commanders juſt dropt from behind a Coach at <hi>White-Hall</hi> into the Service of the Navy, miſerably abus'd in being turn'd over from one Ship to another (contrary to the Rules of Humanity, and the Cuſtom of the Navy) ſo that after they have been at Sea ſeveral years, are hurried out again without Liberty ſo much as to ſee their Relations. Now all things conſider'd, What Encouragement have Mariners to ſerve their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152409:4"/>Country in the Navy? The only thing they have a ſeeming Certainty of is their Meat and Drink, and to be cheated of that too is the Devil.</p>
            <p>The Parliaments of <hi>England</hi> have always made a generous Allowance for the maintenance of the Sailors, and eſpecially upon the Account of Victual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: but conſidering how damnably Funds are clipt, how many hands Mony paſſes through, and every one of them muſt have a ſnack out of it, it is no wonder if our Sailors Guts are pinch'd, and appear like half ſtarv'd Mortals, rather reſembling the carv'd wooden Images in the Stern than the Ship's Crew. Go to <hi>Smithfield</hi> firſt, and ſee there the Oxen bought, and very modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compute the Buyers Snip out of 'em to be 60000 <hi>l.</hi> ſince the Revolution; follow the Cattel to the Victualling-Office, and ſee an undeſcended Wretch there receiving them, advanc'd from thredbare Clothes ſince the Revolution to the Sum of twenty thouſand Pound got out of a Salary of eighty Pounds <hi>per annum;</hi> beſides a Journy-man Apothecary, and a Skipper at the Board, rais'd from abject Nothing to wonderful Pomp. Theſe things conſider'd, the Sailors muſt make ſmall Meals; and it dos plainly demonſtrate how our Funds become deficient, when ſo many obſcure Perſons of no intrinſick Value or Worth muſt get Eſtates out of them. But to proceed to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Victualling ſince the Revolution.</p>
            <p>Soon after the Revolution and the honourable Fight off <hi>Beachy,</hi> Sir <hi>John Parſons</hi> and Company, the then Commiſſioners of the Victualling, were complain'd againſt in Parliament for poiſoning the Sailors, by putting Guts in the Beer, and Galls in the packing of the Fleſh, which put the Sailors into a Flux, whereof great numbers of them dy'd: The Commiſſioners in their own Juſtification alledg'd, That the Beer being ropy, as often it is, and recovers it ſelf again, might occaſion that Miſtake by ſome ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Sailors: That the Galls happened in the packing by reaſon of ſome Bags of Galls that broke on board the Ship, from whence the Salt was taken, wherewith the Fleſh was packed. I ſhall neither juſtify nor condemn thoſe Commiſſioners; but I always wonder'd how Galls ſhould have different Virtues by Sea and Land, for that very year I was cured in <hi>Ireland</hi> of a violent bloody Flux, by taking Powder of Galls: However hereupon Sir <hi>John</hi> and the reſt were diſmiſs'd from their Imployments. This Remove always ſeem'd to me to be made by ſome Perſons to make room for the preſent Commiſſioners; nor do I believe the preſent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners themſelves think their Predeceſſors guilty of any Crime: for up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Eſtabliſhment of the preſent Commiſſion, thoſe very Perſons that put the Guts in the Beer and Galls into the Cask, were continued in their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the only Favourites of the preſent Commiſſion, ſo that Sir <hi>John Parſons</hi> and Company were to bear the Sins of the whole Office, as King <hi>James</hi> did of the whole Nation, none ſuffering for Male-Adminiſtration but himſelf.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:152409:5"/>
            <p>But the chief Deſign of this Paper being an Account of the preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the Victualling, I ſhall relate it with all the Candor and Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs that becomes a Chriſtian and an Engliſhman, as in Duty I am bound by thoſe natural Ties and Obligations which lie upon me to the Service of my Country, and redreſſing the Grievances of injur'd Seamen. In order to which I ſhall conſider how the King and Nation have been ſerved in the Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alling, and what Proviſion has been made for Seamen during the War.</p>
            <p>You'l ſay perhaps it's no News to hear that the King and Nation are cheated, ſince we have had a continued Series of Villany in Publick Offices with Impunity. But from the Victualling we might expect better things, where not only Honeſty, but Religion is pretended; yet the Godly are liable to Temptations, and an Ounce of Virtue is a precious Commodity amongſt ſome ſort of People. A certain Perſon muſt be a very honeſt Man, becauſe the Diſſenting Preachers about <hi>London</hi> vouch for his honeſty; and as mighty Zealots as they were in the late Reigns for Liberty and Property, and againſt Courtiers in the Houſe of Commons and Penſionary Parliaments, can now join with the Wicked to commit Iniquity, and ſhove their heavy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars'd Hearers to <hi>Guild Hall</hi> to vote for a Courtier, and give their recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatory Epiſtles to the Church at <hi>Dover</hi> on behalf of the ſage Politician the Son. But particular Reflections are ſomewhat beſides my purpoſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall offer Obſervations on their Service to the Country in the Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Victualling.</p>
            <p>Their Contracts with the Dealers to the Office have been the moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous of any thing in the World. <hi>Thomas Middleton</hi> a Hogman told me, he one year contracted with the Commiſſioners for a number of Hogs, by which Contract he gained betwixt four and five thouſand Pounds: That the next year (as I remember) he made another Contract for a number of Hogs, by which Contract he was a loſer, the Markets riſing higher than uſual; at the end of the ſeaſon when the whole Complement of Hogs were kill'd, he complain'd of his Loſs to the Commiſſioners, who made an Intereſt with the Lords of the Treaſury, who in conſideration of his loſs gave 2500 <hi>l.</hi> out of the King's Pocket. Who would not enter into Contract with the King, who is willing to bear all the Loſs and have no ſhare of Profit? This <hi>Thomas Middleton</hi> being burdened with Riches, took an occaſion to hang himſelf, and was ſucceeded in Contract by <hi>Henry Nunalee,</hi> who upon a Contract of Hogs loſt 1500 <hi>l.</hi> He went the ſame way as <hi>Middleton</hi> had done; but <hi>Nunalce</hi> being a Williamite, and well affected to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, met with more Rubs and Obſtacles than the other who was a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd Jacobite: However after much attendance, and (I ſuppoſe) paiment of a little Civility Mony, he got an allowance for the Loſs. The Caſe is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152409:5"/>plain on the King's part, that he is a Loſer by ſuch a Contract; and as the Commiſſioners cannot be juſtified in ſuch a Contract, ſo the Reaſon of it on their part is very difficult to be found. For when they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted with Mr. <hi>Nunalee</hi> for the Parcel of Hogs before-mentioned, Pork was at half a Crown a Stone in the Markets, a riſing Price too: It was no Maſt Year, all manner of Hog Grain exceſſive dear, the Seaſon ſo far ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, that all the Town and Offal Hogs were kill'd and converted to Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con: however the Commiſſioners, like good Husbands for the King, beat down the Price; and one wiſe Commiſſioner ſaid, that as he return'd out of the Country, he ſaw a hundred Hogs in one Field, and thence rationally concluding there were the like number in every Field in <hi>England,</hi> they brought the Contract down to twenty ſix Shillings <hi>per</hi> hundred Weight. Now if there was any other meaning in this Contract, beſides doing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervice to the Nation, it muſt be this, that at the end of the Seaſon, by putting the Hogman to petition the Treaſury Board to have his Loſs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, they ſhould manifeſt their wonderful Sagacity in biting off the Head of a poor Hogman.</p>
            <p>Such Contracts are equally injurious to the Sailors as to the King; for the Contractor loſing Money every day, muſt make the beſt of his Market, which is buying the worſt Hogs; ſo that very thin and ill ſed Pork, in all likelihood muſt fill the wooden Platters aboard Ship, and the Sailors be fed with the Refuſe of the Markets, who as they do the beſt Service to the Nation, ought to have the beſt Proviſions the Land can produce. Antient Cuſtom and common Uſage in Offices are or ought to be as much obſerved by Officers, as the Laws of a Realm by the Subject; for when old Cuſtoms are broken in Offices, all things are put into confuſion, and Men are at a loſs how to apply themſelves. It has been an old and a rational Cuſtom in our Offices, and always inſerted in the Inſtructions from the Admiralty to dependant Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices upon it, that no Perſon ſhall deal, or be any way concerned in Trade in that Office wherein he receives Salary: But this has been ſo far from the Practice of the Victualling, that ſome of the Commiſſioners and Officers have dealt with the Office either in Shipping or otherwiſe. A great evil at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends this Practice; for Officers paying themſelves, we can't imagine they'l put themſelves laſt upon the Liſt of Paiment; and ſo other Warrants that are in Courſe are poſtpon'd. And it has been obſerv'd that no Office in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> has broken the Courſe of Paiment more than that of the Victualling: Beſides, ſome of the Officers are common Buyers and Sellers of the Office Bills, and as conſtant Brokers upon the Exchange, as any that deal in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer Notes, Bank Bills or Tallies.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:152409:6"/>
            <p>It is now become a Cuſtom (I believe throughout the whole Navy) for the Cathiers and Clerks to take Poundage of the Perſons they pay Money to, contrary to antient Cuſtom, and all the Equity in the World. The Victual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for ſome time had a Banker in <hi>Lombard-ſtreet,</hi> who paid Money upon the King's Account, and took Poundage of the Perſons he paid it to, as did their Agent at <hi>Portſmouth.</hi> This muſt be either a very great Exaction upon the Parties dealing to the Office, or elſe an Allowance is made for it in the Price of the Commodity, which is a downright Abuſe to the Nation.</p>
            <p>That the Nation has been cheated and abus'd more ſince the Revolution than under any other Government, is evident to any thinking man. The Miſmanagements of the Victualling have been ſo great, and the Office ſo ſcandalous, that it has been even a national Nuſance; and tho pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted with reiterated Complaints at the Treaſury and Parliament, all the honeſt Endeavours of Mankind have prov'd ineffectual: for where Men are Judges of their own Cauſe, no Juſtice can be expected: You'l ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hang a Highway-man more, if you allow him to be tried by his own Troop. About four years ago ſome honeſt Men in the Victualling had made a Diſcovery of ſeveral Embezelments, of which they complained in divers Articles againſt the Officers embezelling the King's Stores. Theſe Articles were delivered to one of the Commiſſioners, and ſo to another, but never examin'd into: All the puniſhment they inflicted on him was, that about a week after the Complaint, they gave him liberty for the Summer to reſide at his Country Houſe, and order'd the Officer that complain'd againſt him to do duty in his Room: This is much of the ſame nature of another Complaint againſt one of their Officers for drinking K. <hi>James</hi>'s Health, who in a Fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night afterwards was advanced from a Place of forty Pounds <hi>per Ann.</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout three or four hundred. A Perſon of Honour hearing how the foreſaid Complaint was ſtifled by the Commiſſioners of the Victualling, got a Copy thereof, and gave it to the Lords of the Treaſury, who after ſome time heard the Commiſſioners <hi>ex parte</hi> againſt the King, and never examined one Witneſs on the King's part, to the proof of the matter of Fact alledged in the ſaid Articles. So that hitherto it has been in vain to complain of Griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, and the People of <hi>England</hi> have been forc'd to maintain by the ſweat of their Brows, many that formerly betray'd their Liberties, and now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich themſelves out of the publick ſpoils of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>To recount all Miſmanagements in this Office would fill a large Volume; the Ignorance and Negligence of the Perſons concern'd in it, the profuſe waſting of the Nation's Stores, the contriving and forming Perquiſites out of the ſame to themſelves, contrary to former Cuſtom and Practice; the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernumerary Officers and Labourers in the Yards, old and decrepid, fitter for Hoſpitals than Service, are things notorious in the Eyes of all but ſuch as ſhould
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152409:6"/>puniſh them. Indeed ſuch Men are well ſecured in ill Practices; they have their Brethren in other Offices to ſtand by them, and a Power of diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch of the Office as complain againſt them, as they did ſeveral of the poor men that complain'd againſt them in Parliament laſt year; nay one of the Commiſſioners threatned to diſcharge one of them in the Speaker's Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber before the Committee.</p>
            <p>Thus this Office has been managed in reſpect to the good of the Nation. It will not now be amiſs to conſider how far this Management has affected the poor Sailors: An Engliſh man is not hard-hearted enough to reflect on the miſerable Condition of our poor Sailors of Admiral <hi>Nevil</hi>'s Squadron in the <hi>Weſt Indies.</hi> I am credibly inform'd from good hands, that out of that Squadron in a very ſhort time we loſt above 2500 men, whoſe Lives I am ſure were of more value and concern to the Engliſh Nation, than all the Advantages of that Expedition, and the mighty Buſineſs of <hi>Cartagena</hi> our Gazette made ſuch a noiſe about. A hot Country, ſtinking Meat, and maggoty Bread, with the noiſom and poiſonous Scent of the Bilge Water, have made many a brave Engliſh Sailor food for Crabs and Sharks.</p>
            <p>Now I am victualling abroad, ſuffer me to take a view of the Navy in the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> under the Command of Admiral <hi>Ruſſel:</hi> I ſhall not touch too far upon this Head, the Affair being in better Hands, and under the conſideration of wiſer-Heads; I mean before the Parliament. But as a Sailor, I muſt needs ſay if ſo large a Sum of Money as is talk'd of was impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſome body upon the account of Beverage, it is a damn'd ſhame that our Fleet ſhould be ſo ſcandalous as it was there, and go by the name of the Vinegar Fleet, by reaſon of the ſour Wine they drank: Beſides, I remember it was a believ'd Report aboard our Ships, that the Spaniards were oblig'd by Articles to find Beverage and dry Proviſions for the Engliſh Fleet; and we all concluded the vaſt Sums of Money brought aboard the Fleet by the victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alling Pinnace, had been upon that account: The Cockſwain and ſome of the Pinnace's Crew once told me how many Tun of Plate they brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board the Fleet; but that and a hundred Rogueries beſide in that Fleet are out of my head at preſent: yet this I can aſſure you, the Folk concerned in buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Beverage got very pretty Eſtates out of it; and old nonſenſical <hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrey</hi> had ſenſe enough to get, as we computed, at leaſt ten thouſand Pounds, when I am well ſatisfied if the Lords of the Admiralty would have been graciouſly pleaſed to have kept him at home, and given him twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Pounds for ſo doing, it would have been more for the advantage of the Nation, and the Sailors Welfare: for we have abundance of men in publick Offices, that it would be for the advantage of the Country to give 'em twice the Salary to be without their Service. Thus has it far'd with the poor Sail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors abroad.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:152409:7"/>
            <p>Now let us look into the Channel, and ſee how our Summer and Winter Guards of Shipping have been victualled. I thank God <hi>England</hi> is a very plentiful Country, and an honeſt Man that has money in his Pocket need not go with an empty Stomach; and I think the Parliaments have always made as ample Proviſion for Victualling as may be; and yet during this War our Fleet has been put to ſhort Allowance in the Channel, have had their guts pinch'd in view of the moſt plentiful Country in the World, an unparallel'd and barbarous Action hitherto unknown. This is bad enough, but to be fed with ſtinking Beef and Pork is much worſe; and yet in the Year 91 or 92 the Victualling Office was turn'd into <hi>Pandora</hi>'s Box, and emitted as many Poiſons to the deſtruction of the poor Seamen, who were fed with rotten and ſtinking Meat, as the Purſers Surveys, and the Books at the Victualling-Office at <hi>Dover</hi> will teſtifie. It was not the nature of the Climate made theſe Proviſions ſtink, this we are certain of, and as certain that it was done ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of a wilful Deſign againſt the Sailors, or out of profound Ignorance, both which are very dangerous.</p>
            <p>It ſeems as if <hi>England</hi> was ſtill to be perplex'd with a continued Series of ill Practices, and that the poor Sailors our chiefeſt Strength were to be abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to all the Miſeries of human Life, and as if every one that has a ſuperin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendency over them, by that Power had a Right to abuſe them: they learn one of the other to make earnings of them, and at the ſame time get Mony out of the King's Pocket and thoſe poor Creatures Bellies. Our Advices from Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral <hi>Aylmer</hi>'s Squadron affirm their having Iriſh Beef inſtead of Engliſh: without doubt Engliſh Beef bears a good Price in thoſe Parts, and is a very Merchantable Commodity. It has always been contrary to the Cuſtom of the Navy to victual with any other Proviſions than what are received from the King's Stores, as long as ſuch Proviſions ſhall laſt: and the Purſers of Ships are obliged to furniſh the Ship with ſuch Proviſions as are ſpecified in their ſeveral Indents, for which before they gave Security at the Navy Board. Indeed it may be allowable for the Purſers of Ships in foreign Parts, where they can afford it, to victual with freſh Proviſions, this change being not detrimental to the King but ſerviceable to the Sailors overrun with the Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy. And having before given Security for the Victualling of the Ship, in this Caſe the Proviſions have been adjudg'd to be their own, and they have been impowred to ſell them for their own Advantage, but not without the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander's Warrant for ſo doing; tho I have known the King's Proviſions ſold in the River of <hi>Thames,</hi> which, if there had been any left upon Return from a Voyage, ought to have been return'd into the King's Stores from whence they were firſt iſſued. The Commanders of Ships formerly had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with the Ships Proviſions, any further than to overlook and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152409:7"/>the Purſer, that none of them were converted any otherways than to the uſe of the Ship; but now it ſeems the Commanders have uſurp'd a Power in this Caſe, altogether detrimental to the Sailors: there is now as ill a Cuſtom brought up in the Navy for the Commanders to receive the Ships neceſſary Money which always was the Purſers Charge, and for which they always indented with the Clerk of the Iſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in the Victualling, being one Article amongſt the ſeveral Species of Proviſions ſpecified in their Indent. But the Commanders being willing for their own Intereſt to have every thing in their own hands, have gain'd this Point upon the Purſers, not to their own diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. Now the Commander only having the Charge of the Ship, and giving no Security, being charg'd with nothing elſe, it's impracticable for him to receive the neceſſary Money, the Purſer having before given Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity for the ſame.</p>
            <p>If there had not been ſo great Care in the Victualling to get Eſtates, there might have been more Care taken in getting good and wholeſom Proviſions for the Service of the Navy: but any thing is thought fit Food for Sailors, who being long accuſtomed to bad Diet, hardly know when they are ill us'd. But indeed the Care of the Victualling requires ſomething of Brains; and as Times and Seaſons alter, ſo muſt Methods too, for a common Road may lead a Man to the Place he intends to go, tho common Reaſon might direct him a nearer and perhaps a cleanlier way, if his Judgment was ſutable to his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity. But Men of ſmall Reaſon are often the greateſt Opiniat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs, and think the Exerciſe of their Talent outdoes all Mankind, when their Actions weigh'd in the Ballance of Reaſon are lighter than the loweſt degree of vanity. I refer it to the Judgment of any rational Man whether the Method now us'd in the Victualling in diſſolving the Rock Salt into Pickle, and therewith pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their Meat for Sea Service, be conſiſtent with Reaſon and the health of the Sailors: we know they are neither Conjurers nor Philoſophers, yet a ſmall degree of knowledg will tell a Man, that Pickle with all the ill qualities of Salt in it, can never be wholeſom for human Bodies, which the Rock Salt muſt of neceſſity have before refining. The Bittern, the moſt noxious Quality in Salt, is ſeparated only by Precipitation; and this Quality joyn'd with a ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurous Arſenick in the Rock, and embodied with the moiſture of the Meat, if it ſuit the Victuallers Intereſt, it can never agree with the Welfare of the Sailor. Mr. <hi>Collins</hi> in his Diſcourſe of Salt, <hi>p.</hi> 55. ſpeaking of its vicious Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, ſays as to Fleſh, <hi>Beſides in general a bad Taſte, or a good Reliſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd, the Moiſture, Gravy, and Nouriſhment in a little time is rendred as ſalt as Salt it ſelf. Hence the Fleſh becomes hard, afterwards very bad or unfit for Food, and at length is mortified or rotten.</hi> He further adds as to the Conſequences of uſing it: <hi>It cauſes Scurvies, Conſumptions, and other
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152409:8"/>Acrimonious Diſeaſes in the Bodies of Seamen, or Soldiers in a beſieged Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that are compell'd to the frequent and long uſe of it.</hi> Nay it is of ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and corroding a Nature, that the Honourable <hi>Robert Boyl</hi> Eſq; has ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd it, as to make it diſſolve Iron Bars: but perhaps the Victualler thinks the Sailors Bodies more durable than Iron, and becauſe their Patience cannot be worn out, their Guts can't neither. There's no great danger that any Body will follow this fooliſh Example; however herein they have manifeſted their kindneſs to the King and Country in uſing a Method that leſſens the Duty upon Salt, conſidering how many Weigh of Salt is us'd in Pickle in one Year: and it is very unſeemly that a Project deſtructive of a publick Fund, ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence at the King's own Houſe as an Example to the Subject; but the whole Management of the Navy is of a piece. The <hi>Simeon</hi>'s and <hi>Levi</hi>'s, tho of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Tribes, are embarked in the ſame Cauſe, purſue the ſame Ends, and are alike odious in the eyes of the People.</p>
            <p>But the miſmanagements of this Office and of the Navy, proceed from the Admiralty, as filthy Springs from an impure Fountain, theſe being but branches of that curſed Tree, that has yielded the Nation ſuch ſowr fruit, as to ſet all our Sailors teeth on edg: an Office manag'd we know not how, nor to what purpoſe; for I dare engage to pick out as many old Women in <hi>Wapping,</hi> that ſhould have manag'd that Affair more for the Honour, Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Advantage of the Engliſh Nation. The Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> when ſhe gave her Viſit to <hi>Solomon,</hi> extol'd his Wiſdom and his Servants: our <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> is indeed worthy of Honour, who has been the Care of Heaven, as theſe Nations have been his; and the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> might juſtly have done him the ſame Honour could ſhe have come hither: yet I engage ſhe would have left out the latter part of her Compliment, and took little notice of the <hi>Sitting of his Servants</hi> in the Admiralty, of their Virtue or Wiſdom: She takes no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s nor <hi>Hiram's</hi> Navy, yet the Scripture tells us they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Conduct <hi>of Ship-Men that had knowledg of the Sea;</hi> and in another place, that part of their Loading was Apes and Peacocks, but tells us no where that Apes or Peacocks had the Sovereign Command in Sea Affairs, or that Land men were proper Perſons to command Men of War. It is a great Misfortune to a Prince to fall into the hands of Sycophants and Flatterers, who magnifie their own deſerts to the Ruin of the Nation, get about him ſo cloſe that his beſt Subjects can't ſee him; and if he be unfairly dealt with they know nothing of it, neither how to commiſerate his Condition, nor give him that Aſſiſtance as is neceſſary to his preſervation: ſuch a Prince is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly hoodwink'd like a Hawk, and thoſe that hold him will not let him fly, but at ſome profitable Quarry for their own Advantage; they never ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to hear what others can ſay, leſt they ſhould ſpeak ſomething to their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152409:8"/>own Prejudice. And thus the Prince by adhering to and promoting the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of a few, loſes the Love of many, which often proves fatal both to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and People. A Good Prince diſpenſes his Favours as the Sun does its Beams by a univerſal Reflection upon Plants of all ſorts, but the more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Plants receive moſt of the kindly Influence of its Rays. Mercy is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable thing in a Prince, it may drop upon Criminals, but Favours ought not to pour down upon them. I would not deſtroy the whole Species of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers becauſe they are part of the Creation, and manifeſt the Wiſdom of the great Former of all things; but there is no neceſſity for me to foſter them in my Boſom, and expoſe my Body to their Poiſon. If the Managers of the Admiralty deſerve the Poſts they occupy, it is more than the People know, and the Merchants of <hi>England</hi> will tell lamentable Stories to the contrary. Some of them perhaps have deſerv'd well of their Country, however not in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miralty: for a Perſon prefer'd to an Office he knows nothing of, by his Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in one day may do more diſſervice to his Country, than all the former Services of his Life will amount to. The wiſeſt Men in <hi>England</hi> have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd their Brains to no purpoſe, to unriddle the meaning of ſuch Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; the old Maxim of preferring Enemies and diſobliging Friends has been exploded by all Men of Senſe: but the Court Party have now another Maxim, that all Commonwealths Men are Enemies to Monarchy, and not to be truſted; and all Engliſhmen and Lovers of the Liberties of their Country they repreſent as ſuch, while the contrary get the beſt Places of Profit and Truſt in the Kingdom. Now I would fain know how this Government comes to be a Monarchy in their Senſe, and whether any Commonwealths<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in <hi>England</hi> can deſire a Government more ſutable to the common Good, and conform to his own Principles, if it be faithfully adminiſtr'd according to its Conſtitution. For no Man of a Republican Principle can deſire more than to have Kings accountable to the People for Male-Adminiſtration, and by their forefaulting to make a Forfeiture of the Regal Dignity wherewith they are veſted; by which Forfeiture all the Right of Governing devolves again up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the People, who of their own free Will and undoubted Right and Power proceed to a New Election, and place one more Righteous than the former up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Throne if they think fit, upon which Foundation this Government is built. So that Commonwealthſmen, as the Courtiers call them, muſt be the beſt Friends of this Government, becauſe they are for ſecuring the Foundation of it, and not for raiſing a Superſtructure to make it top-heavy and tumble down. Ill and corrupt Officers and Miniſters are the greateſt Enemies to Monarchy in the World: for when the People ſee under all Kings ill Men in Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, the Wealth of the Nation profuſely laviſh'd, and the Liberties of the People in continual danger, they'l conclude that Miſmanagements are acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152409:9"/>inſeparable from Monarchy, that the Fault is not in the King but in the Office, and let 'em change the Perſon never ſo often, the thing will be the ſame; and ſo begin to think of another form of Government.</p>
            <p>There has been ſuch an uninterrupted Progreſs of Miſmanagements in our Naval Affairs, through the Conduct of the Perſons concerned in the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagery, that nothing hitherto has been our preſervation, but the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate hand of Providence: The Walls of our Iſland are our Shipping; thoſe once broken down, we are laid open to the violent Inſults of any Enemy: A little Retroſpection now would do very well, and not only ſo, but we ought to look forward, and find out ways and means to prevent the like for the future.</p>
            <p>It is the Buſineſs of our Repreſentatives in Parliament to enquire into things of this Nature; they are the Guardians of our Liberties, and are bound to redreſs the Grievances of the People, by virtue of whoſe electing Power they have a Right to ſit in the Houſe of Commons and enact Laws: They have no Power from the People they repreſent to make Laws deſtructive of their Property, or diminiſhing of their Wealth, upon groundleſs Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; nor ought they to give Releaſes to ſuch as have ſquander'd away the Wealth of the Kingdom, and betray'd the Liberty of the Subject. He that dos not prevent a Miſchief when it lies in his power ſo to do, is equally guilty with the hand that did it, and equally accountable to God Almighty. It is much more now the Buſineſs of Parliaments, ſince there is no way elſe to bring Criminals to Juſtice; and the greateſt Juſtice that ever was done in Caſes of this nature has been done by Parliaments, of which I could give many Inſtances had I time or place. Making publick Examples of ſuch Criminals is not only a Debt we owe to publick Juſtice, and the common good of the Realm, but will be a Terror to all future Offenders in Caſes of the like Nature: for if ſuch Abuſes are tolerated too long, they'l become faſhionable, and a Man muſt turn a Rogue to get into an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploiment. 'Tis well for the Engliſh Nation theſe Miſcreants are not beyond the Reach of Parliament, whoſe Authority and Prerogative if once loſt we may bid an eternal Farewel to our Native Liberty; and indeed the leſſening of the Power of Parliaments has not a little been aim'd at by ſome within theſe few years, who would have us believe the Buſineſs of the Commons is only to aſſemble one year in St. <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Chappel to raiſe Mony for them to ſquander it away the next; I wonder all this while they have not had the Impudence to attempt the raiſing of Mony without Act of Parliament, that being as legal as the converting appropriated Funds to other uſes than ſuch as are ſpecify'd in the Act. But the day of Judgment we hope is at hand, when the Wiſdom and ſupream Authority of the People ſhall avenge the Injuries done to the Engliſh Nation upon the Criminals.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:152409:9"/>
            <p>To look forward is as much our Intereſt; and no leſs the indiſpenſible Duty of our Repreſentatives in Parliament to take care of the ſafety of the Nation in the well management of the Fleet. His Majeſty in his moſt Gracious Speech upon disbanding the Army, lays the ſafety of the Nation before them, <hi>as a Duty incumbent on them;</hi> and ſince the Army is disband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, our main ſafety is our Shipping. This Security ſuppoſed, was, I believe, the chief reaſon of laying the Land Forces aſide; ſo that now the beſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity we have left is our Shipping, and a good and ſufficient Security too under a good Management. The Nation has already felt the Effects of the preſent Management; and to let the Nation ſuffer any longer upon this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count may bring us under ſuch ill Circumſtances, that will put it out of the Power of Parliaments to recover us from ruin. The Admiralty has been in the hands of ſuch Men too long already, and 'tis now more dangerous than ever to repoſe a Truſt of ſo high a Nature, of ſuch great Conſequence to the Nation, in their hands; we know very well what Party it was inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo much upon the Neceſſity of a Land Force: and to truſt the Navy in ſuch hands for the future, as already it has been of ill Conſequence, ſo it may prove more dangerous; they may ſo far embaraſs the Naval Affairs, retard the Enterprizes of the Navy, by ordering Squadrons and Cruizers in ſuch Stations where they cannot be ſerviceable: ſo that in a little time the Navy doing no ſervice, ſhall be thought altogether uſeleſs, and this ſhall be made an Argument for the neceſſity of a Land Army. I wiſh the Miſcarriages of the Navy already have not been out of deſign for this Purpoſe: If theſe Grievances continue, the Commons may at laſt be forc'd to prevent ſuch Miſchiefs for the future by taking the Charge and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the Navy and dependant Offices into their own hands, by appointing Commiſſioners of their own: and this ſeems rational enough for thoſe that are at the Charge, to ſuperintend the Management of the Affair; nor is this a new thing and unprecedented. 31 <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Salisbury, John</hi> Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury, John</hi> Earl of <hi>Worceſter, James</hi> Earl of <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Sturton were appointed by Parliament to keep the Seas;</hi> and the Tunnage and Poundage were appointed for defraying the Charge thereof. 8 <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. The Merchants were empowered to name two Perſons, the one for the South, the other for the North, <hi>who by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion had the like Power as other Admirals had.</hi> So that you ſee the Charge of the Navy has been a Parliamentary Care in times leſs dangerous than now; and thoſe who are appointed Commiſſioners in this Affair will be more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the diſcharge of the Truſt repoſed in them, nor will they have ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ways to ſlip their Necks out of the Collar as now: Here will be no Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Seal to impreſt Money for unknown Services, no paſſing of Accounts
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152409:10"/>without Vouchers, no abuſe of Sailors in Wages or Proviſions; the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom will be kept in a good Poſture of Defence; the Minds of the People will be eaſy when the Management of their Navy is in the hands of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of their own, alike intereſted in the Good and Security of the Realm; and our Enemies more terrified, when the Buſineſs of the Navy is the Care of the whole Kingdom. All which is ſubmitted to the Wiſdom of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives in Parliament, before whom the Caſe lies at this Juncture.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>
               <hi>A Catalogue of Books written againſt a Standing Army, and ſold by</hi> A. Balwin.</head>
            <p>AN Argument ſhewing, that a Standing Army is inconſiſtent with a Free Government, and abſolutely deſtructive to the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Engliſh Monarchy. In 2 Parts. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>A Letter from the Author of the Argument againſt a Standing Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, to the Author of the Ballancing Letter. Price 3 <hi>d.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>Some Queries for the better underſtanding K. <hi>James</hi>'s Liſt of 18000 Iriſh Heroes publiſhed at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> in anſwer to what had bin, and what ſhould be writ againſt a Standing Army. Price 1 <hi>d.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe concerning Government with relation to Militias. Price 6 <hi>d.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>The Militia Reform'd, or an eaſy Scheme of furniſhing <hi>England</hi> with a conſtant Land Force, capable to prevent or to ſubdue any Foreign Power, and to maintain perpetual Quiet at home, without endangering the Publick Liberty. The 2d Edition. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>A ſhort Hiſtory of Standing Armies in <hi>England.</hi> The 3d Edition. Price 6 <hi>d.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>A Confutation of a late Pamphlet intituled, A Letter ballancing the Neceſſity of keeping up a Land Force in times of Peace, with the Dangers that may follow on it. Part I. The 2d Edition. Price 6 <hi>d.</hi> The Second Part, being a Vindication of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> will be ſpeedily publiſh'd.</p>
            <p>A Letter to a Member of Parliament concerning Guards and Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons. Price 2 <hi>d.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>A 2d Letter concerning the four Regiments commonly called Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reeners. Price 3 <hi>d.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>The Seaman's Opinion of a Standing Army, in oppoſition to a Fleet at Sea as the beſt ſecurity of the Kingdom. In a Letter to a Merchant written by a Sailor. The 3d Edition. Price 6 <hi>d.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>Some further Conſiderations concerning a Standing Army. Pr. 3 <hi>d.</hi> 
            </p>
            <p>The State of the Caſe, or the Caſe of the State. Price 1 <hi>d.</hi> 
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152409:10"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
